<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of such things as were obserued to happen in the iourney of the right Honourable Charles Earle of Nottingham, L. High Admirall of England, his highnesse ambassadour to the King of Spaine being sent thither to take the oath of the sayd King for the maintenance of peace betweene the two famous kings of Great Brittaine and Spaine: according to the seuerall articles formerly concluded on by the constable of Castilla in England in the moneth of August, 1604. Set forth by authoritie.</title>
            <author>[Treswell, Robert].</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13959</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118681</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853888</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853888</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19287</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13959)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19287)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 942:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of such things as were obserued to happen in the iourney of the right Honourable Charles Earle of Nottingham, L. High Admirall of England, his highnesse ambassadour to the King of Spaine being sent thither to take the oath of the sayd King for the maintenance of peace betweene the two famous kings of Great Brittaine and Spaine: according to the seuerall articles formerly concluded on by the constable of Castilla in England in the moneth of August, 1604. Set forth by authoritie.</title>
                  <author>[Treswell, Robert].</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 42 [i.e. 64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Melchisedech Bradwood for Gregorie Seaton, and are to be sold at his shop vnder Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: Rob. Tresvvell.</note>
                  <note>Corrects the account given in STC 13857.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank except for signature-mark "A".</note>
                  <note>P. 64 misnumbered 42.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nottingham, Charles Howard, --  Earl of, ca. 1536-1624.</term>
               <term>England --  Foreign relations --  Spain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Spain --  Foreign relations --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19287:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19287:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A RELATION OF SVCH THINGS AS <hi>were obſerued to happen in the Journey</hi> of the right Honourable CHARLES Earle <hi>of</hi> NOTTINGHAM, <hi>L. High Admirall</hi> of ENGLAND, His Highneſſe <hi>Ambaſſadour to the King</hi> of SPAINE:</p>
            <p>Being ſent thither to take the Oath of the ſayd <hi>King for the maintenance of Peace betweene</hi> the two famous Kings of <hi>Great Brittaine</hi> and <hi>Spaine:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>According to the ſeuerall Articles formerly concluded</hi> on by the Conſtable of <hi>Caſtilla</hi> in <hi>England</hi> in the Moneth of Auguſt, 1604.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Set forth by Authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Melchiſedech Bradwood</hi> for <hi>Gregorie Seaton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop vnder Alderſgate. 1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19287:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19287:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Auing collected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether many gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall obſeruations in that Honourable iourney into <hi>Spain,</hi> lately performed by the right honourable and worthy Earle, The Earle of <hi>Nottingham;</hi> although amongst many reaſons which perſwaded me to be therein to my ſelfe ſecret, and to the world ſparing in diuulging this Treatiſe, I found eſpecially (and which I muſt of neceſsitie confeſſe) mine owne weakeneſſe in compiling the ſame and making it fit and worthy of ſo generall a reading, as by this conſequence it must vndergoe: yet being ouer-weighed with many eſpeciall motiues which I could not well anſwer or contradict, I thought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:19287:3"/> to expoſe my ſelfe to the fauourable cenſure of the worthieſt &amp; beſt minded; (who rather reſpect a plaine and home<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred ſtile, yet true, than a tale conſiſting of eloquent phraſes, but doubtfull) than pleaſing my ſelfe in mine owne fearefull humor, giue cauſe of offence to them whom most I laboured to content. The firſt of theſe motiues being, That many of my friends, knowing me to haue been by eſpeciall appointment an Attendant vpon his Lordſhip in that honourable emploiment, and vnderſtanding of the care taken by me in obſeruing ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars in the ſame; exceedingly vrged me to giue them a perfect knowledge and ſatisfaction thereof: which as it was a thing likely to be tedious, ſo could they not receiue that contentment by a briefe Report, which a more ample Relation
<pb facs="tcp:19287:3"/> and Diſcourſe might better affoord. Another was, That for that it came to our knowledge, how many falſe and ill contriued reports had beene bruted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad after our departure from <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> aſwell derogating from that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable enterteinment we receiued in generall whileſt we were in <hi>Spaine,</hi> as from the proceedings of his Lordſhip and his Company in ſome particulars, I could not but (taxing my ſelfe of dutie to his Lordſhip and the reſt) endeuour to ſatisfie all doubtfull and vnſatisfied minds with relating and declaring the truth thereof. But a third and a more eſpeciall cauſe is, That ſithence our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, one not well informed hauing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken to know much of the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of that Iourney, and mistaking himſelfe in his own vnderſtanding, late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:19287:4"/> publiſhed a Pamphlet of many falſe and erroneous obſeruations: therby poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsing the Readers with an vntrue Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of that, the trueth whereof they ſo much deſired. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon theſe former conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations therfore, I was aduiſed to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnto your generous acceptance my wel-meaning endeuors; which although they cannot giue that pleaſure and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in reading you happily expect, yet ſhall they aſſure you what they promiſe: That is; A true Relation of ſuch things which happened in that honorable Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. In reporting whereof, I had rather be condemned for plainneſſe, than once ſuſpected for reporting an vntrueth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ROB. TRESVVELL, aliâs SOMERSET, Herauld.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19287:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A RELATION OF</hi> ſuch things as were obſerued to happen <hi>in the Iourney of the right Honourable CHARLES</hi> Earle of <hi>NOTTINGHAM, &amp;c. his Higneſſe Ambaſſadour to the King of SPAINE,</hi> being ſent thither to take the Oath of the ſayd King for <hi>the maintenance of Peace betweene the two famous</hi> Kings of <hi>GREAT BRITTAIN</hi> and <hi>SPAIN,</hi> according to the ſeuerall Articles formerly concluded on by the Conſtable of <hi>Caſtilla</hi> in <hi>England</hi> in the Moneth of August <hi>1604.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>O ſoone as the right honorable <hi>Charles</hi> Earle of <hi>Nottingham</hi> L. High Admirall of <hi>England</hi> had taken notice from his Maieſty, That it was his will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to employ him in this great Ambaſſage to the K. of <hi>Spaine,</hi> calling to minde, how honourably and richly the Duke of <hi>Fryas,</hi> Conſtable of <hi>Caſtilla</hi> &amp; late Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour for the ſaid king, had formerly demeaned him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19287:5"/> in <hi>England:</hi> preſently, with a moſt honourable reſolution, neither fearing the hazard of his perſon, being now aged, nor regarding the expences, that ſo great and honourable an employment ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: with what ſpeed he conueniently might, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoured to performe his Maieſties deſignes and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment heerein. And therefore by the aduice of the Councell of <hi>England,</hi> he firſt reſolued both what honourable perſonages and what number of them might be fitting, for accompanying and attending him, in this his great imployment. To whom when as particular Letters from the Councell, by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties eſpeciall commandement were diſpatched, to giue them notice, to prepare themſelues to attend the ſaid Noble Earle according as his Highneſſe had commanded; they ſeemed ſo willing and readie to performe their duty and ſeruice therein, that his Lordſhip was farre more troubled to denie many, and that of very good ſort, who voluntarily tendered their ſeruice in good will and honour of his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to attend him in this his appointed voyage, than he was at firſt in bethinking what company were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to take with him. And therefore at laſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding of a competent number, (not without di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpleaſing many) he reſolued vpon theſe whoſe names heereafter follow:
<list>
                  <item>The Earle of <hi>Pearth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Lord <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Effingham</hi> his ſonne and heire.</item>
                  <item>The Lord <hi>Willoughbey.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The Lord <hi>Norrys.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19287:5"/>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Charles Howard</hi> knight, his ſecond ſonne.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Howard</hi> knight, ſecond ſonne to the Earle of <hi>Suffolke.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Sheffeild</hi> knight, ſonne and heire to the Lord <hi>Sheffeild.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Maſter <hi>Pickering Wotton,</hi> ſonne and heire to the Lord <hi>Wotton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Richard Lewſon</hi> knight, Admirall of the fleet and Viceadmirall of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Maſter <hi>Thomas Compton,</hi> brother to the Lord <hi>Compton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hans Herman Van Veiſcenbach,</hi> a German, and of good eſteeme in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Robert Drewry.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Robert Maunſell,</hi> Treaſurer of the kings Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy, and Vice admirall of the fleet.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Edward Howard</hi> his nephew.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Palmer.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Edward Swift.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William Smith.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Treuor,</hi> ſurueyor of the nauy.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Robert Killegrew.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Richard Cowper,</hi> Gentleman-porter of the Kings houſe.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>George Buc.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Guylford Slingsby.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Adolfus Cary.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Francis Howard,</hi> his Lordſhips nephew alſo.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Sackuyle Treuor,</hi> Rereadmirall of the fleet.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Walter Gore.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19287:6"/>
                  <item>Sir <hi>William Page.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Giles Hoftman.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Thomas Roe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Eyres.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Phillip Cary.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Henry Knowles.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>Iohn Gueuarra.</hi> Knights.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Giles Porter</hi> his interpreter. Doctor <hi>Marbeck.</hi> Doctor <hi>Palmer,</hi> Phyſitians. Maſter <hi>Pawlet.</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Cary.</hi> Maſter <hi>Barret.</hi> Maſter <hi>Iohn Lewſon. Lewis Treſham.</hi> Captaine <hi>Thomas Button. William Button. Iohn Fearne. Hierom Laments. Henry But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. Iohn Milliſcent. Bernard Saunders. Philip Roper. Francis Plomb. Roger Tailor.</hi> Captaine <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Morgan. Henry Minn. Chriſtopher Fredericke. Thomas Buc.</hi> Captaine <hi>William Polewheele. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Fittou. Walter Grey. Iohn Atkinſon. Dudley Carleton. Edward Smith,</hi> and many other gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of good condition and quality aſwell his Lordſhips priuate Officers and Seruants, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers whoſe names are not heerein remembred.</p>
            <p>The ſhips appointed to attend his Lordſhip and his company for tranſportation of themſelues, the followers and neceſſaries, were theſe: <list>
                  <item>The Beare. being ſhippes royall.</item>
                  <item>The Dew-repulſe. being ſhippes royall.</item>
                  <item>The Waſt-ſpight. being ſhippes royall.</item>
                  <item>The Mary-Anne.</item>
                  <item>The Amity.</item>
                  <item>The Reſiſtance.</item>
                  <item>The great Hoy called the George.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:19287:6"/>
            <p>According to appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the ſaid Lords, Knights and Gentlemen prepared themſelues to giue their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance whenſoeuer his Lordſhip ſhould take his iourney, and therefore vnderſtanding that he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to take leaue of the king on Thurſeday the one and twentieth day of <hi>March</hi> according to the compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>England;</hi> the greateſt number of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very richly apparelled themſelues and extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily appointed for their ſeruants, gaue their atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance at <hi>Nottingham</hi> houſe the ſaid one and twentie day of <hi>March,</hi> his Lordſhip hauing appointed many barges and boates for conueying himſelfe, the ſaid lords and knights and their company to the Court, the Kings Highneſſe then being at <hi>Greenwich:</hi> the ſaid Earle hauing ordained his owne company to be in number as followeth: Six Trumpeters clad in O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range colour Damaske, with cloakes of cloth of the ſame colour, and Banners of Damaske with his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours armes thereupon. Six Footemen in Orange Tawny veluet alike ſuted. Six Pages, clad likewiſe in veluet of the ſame colour, with their cloakes ſuteable. Thirty gentlemen with cloakes of blacke veluet. Foureſcore yeomen well apparelled with liuery cloakes of Orange Tawny cloth, garded with ſiluer &amp; blew ſilk lace. The ſaid noble Earle being thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared went with his ſaid company from <hi>Nottingham</hi> houſe the ſaid Thurſday about noone, &amp; ſo ſhooting the bridge, arriued at <hi>Greenwich</hi> immediatly after dinner: and there preſenting himſelfe and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany vnto his Maieſtie, was moſt acceptably and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly enterteined. After ſome time ſpent in recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19287:7"/> his Highneſſe commandement aſwell concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning himſelfe in his owne particular, as alſo touching the conducting and preſenting of Sir <hi>Charles Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wallys</hi> knight, who was appointed for to be his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties liedger Ambaſſadour with the king of <hi>Spaine.</hi> The ſaid Ambaſſadours, Lords, Knights and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men humbly taking their leaues of his Highneſſe were for that night diſmiſſed; euery one taking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to his lodging, there remaining and expecting his Lordſhips further pleaſure to be knowen when they ſhould prepare to ſet forward on this iourney.</p>
            <p>His Lordſhip hauing now diſpatched his priuate counſels and intendments with his Maieſty and the Lords of the Councel, gaue warning to his ſaid com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany and followers to be ready againſt Tueſday mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning being the ſix and twentieth day of the ſaid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of <hi>March.</hi> Which time he gaue to prepare themſelues; for that day he intended to ſet forward. On which ſaid day being both mindfull and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for his intended Iourney, he was early vp in the morning, and taking the time of the tide, and ſuch company as were ready, being to the number of 80. perſons, in diuers barges and boates paſſed from <hi>Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingham</hi> houſe to <hi>Graueſend,</hi> and there dined, ſtaying for much of the company which followed. After din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner they rode from <hi>Graueſend</hi> to <hi>Chatham</hi> where he lodged that night. The ſame night the Earle of <hi>Marre</hi> came from the court of purpoſe to congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late with his Lordſhip, and do ſuch like priuate offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of friendſhip. The next day being wedneſday his Lordſhip would haue gone to the ſhips, which were
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19287:7"/> then fallen ſo low as <hi>Quynborow,</hi> there riding at An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor and ſtaying our comming, but the weather fell out ſomewhat foule and the wind contrary, ſo that he reſted at <hi>Chatham</hi> that night. The next day being Thurſday the eight and twentieth of <hi>March,</hi> before ſeuen of the clocke in the morning his Lordſhip ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing commanded to be ready diuers barges and pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes to carry himſelfe and his followers aboord the ſhips, tooke his barge, and about tenne of the clocke the ſame day entered the ſhip called the Beare, lying in <hi>Quynborow</hi> Road as afore is ſaid, together with the Dew-repulſe and the Waſt-ſpight, which three ſhippes kept company together and lay of purpoſe to tranſport his Lordſhip, the Ambaſſadour Lidger, and the other Lords, Knights and Gentlemen that were of the company and traine.</p>
            <p>Now what by reaſon of ſtaying for ſome of the Lords and Gentlemen, as yet not come a boord, for the better diſpoſing and ordering all things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the voyage, as alſo for placing and appointing to euery man his roome accordingly. The weather likewiſe being not very faire to put to ſea, we Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before <hi>Quinborow</hi> till Sunday morning being Eaſter day and the laſt day of <hi>March.</hi> At which time the wind comming about to the Weſt and ſtanding faire to put to ſea, his Lordſhip commanded to wey and to ſet ſaile, which was done accordingly: Sailing as farre as the tide would giue them leaue, which was to a certaine Road, between the Sands neere to the Shoe Beacon, where they reſted that night. The next day being very foule and the wind contrary,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19287:8"/> they were faine to ride it out til Tueſday morning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſecond of <hi>April.</hi> At what time the weather fell ſomewhat faire, and his Lordſhip being deſirous to take all aduantage that might forward the iourny, commanded to wey againe and put to ſea, but the wind being very ſlacke, he was becalmed and ſo dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to a flatte neere the Spitts, where for that the tide was much ſpent, and the flood comming on, they caſt Ancor about one of the clocke in the afternoone, there ſtaying in expectation of wind till Wedneſday morning, when although there was little or no wind ſtirring, yet his Lordſhip ſet forward, tiding it as far as they could that night. The next day being Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day early in the morning the wind comming ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what towards the North, his Lordſhip cauſed to wey Ancor, and ſo with expence of time and much pains, the ſhippes recouered <hi>Douer</hi> Road, where they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cored aſwell for the receauing in of many of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany as alſo for taking in freſh water and victualls. So ſoone as the fleet was diſcouered and comming neere <hi>Douer</hi> Road, aſwell the forts and blockehouſes as the caſtle of <hi>Douer</hi> ſaluted them with many ſhot: his Lordſhip anſwering them againe both out of his owne ſhip and out of the reſt alſo with the like.</p>
            <p>That night the Lordes and Gentlemen for whom they made ſtay at <hi>Douer</hi> came aboord, and that night alſo his Lordſhip minded to haue ſet forward, had not the Hoie called the <hi>George,</hi> by ſpending of her Maſt, in her paſſage from <hi>Quynborow</hi> to <hi>Douer,</hi> cauſed a longer aboad.</p>
            <p>Now for that the ſaide Hoie was appointed to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19287:8"/> carrie prouiſion and neceſſaries for the fleete, and could not be ſo ſoone made ready againe for ſeruice, as was deſired, and for that, the winde ſtanding at North-eaſt was a faire and fitte winde for going for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: His Lordſhip aduiſed with Sir <hi>Richard Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> the Admirall of the fleet, that ſome courſe might be preſently had to forward the iourney; Sir <hi>Richard</hi> therefore with great care and extraordinarie paines, labouring all that night, being ſeconded by Sir <hi>Iohn Treuor</hi> Surueyor of the Nauie, vnladed the ſaide Hoie, of all ſuch neceſſarie prouiſions as they were like to vſe in the voyage, and hauing that night and the next morning diſperſed her luggage ſome in one ſhippe and ſome in another, and being returned to to the ſhippes, about tenne of the clocke a warning peece was giuen; and about two howers after, they weyed, and ſailed all that day being Friday, the fifth day of Aprill, vntill the next day being Saturday, and then being becalmed, were faine to caſt ancor againe. That night the winde comming faire, they weied ancor, and ſo failed all that night till the next day, the winde againe altering, they lay at anchor till towards the euening, and then ſet forward, ſayling vntill tenne of the clocke the next day, and then caſt ancor. About tenne of the clocke in the euening they weyed ancor againe, and ſo ſailed with a faire winde that night and the next day. On Wedneſday as we ſailed, his Lordſhip commaunded to hayle a Barke which was diſcouered to be a Barke of <hi>Barnſtable</hi> in <hi>Deuonſhire,</hi> and came from <hi>Bayon</hi> in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared for newes that there was a yongue Prince
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19287:9"/> borne in <hi>Spayne.</hi> Now it ſhould ſeeme, his Lordſhip had receaued vnderſtanding by letters from the right Honourable, the Vicount <hi>Cramborne,</hi> his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe principall Secretarie, deliuered to him whileſt we laie at road before <hi>Douer;</hi> that his comming was expected, and prouiſion made for him and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie, by the King of <hi>Spayne</hi> at Saint <hi>Anderas.</hi> His Lordſhip hauing ſent his prouiſion of Horſes, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, Lytters, Hangings, and other his rich furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and neceſſaries: together with his Herbengers and other Officers to the <hi>Groyne</hi> in ſeuerall Hoies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed for that purpoſe: the Kings ſhippe called the <hi>Aduantage,</hi> being their Conuoy. His Highneſſe preſents likewiſe vnder the charge of <hi>Thomas Knoell</hi> one of his Maieſties Ecquery, and appointed meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger for the deliuerie thereof to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> in their ſaid companie. And being vncerteine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Kings deſignes were aſwell knowen to the ſaid Herbengers and the reſt, as to himſelfe: he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded captaine <hi>Morgan,</hi> and one Maſter <hi>Pet</hi> a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Shipwright, and a very good Mariner; to goe on bord the <hi>Reſistance,</hi> being a ſhippe of <hi>London,</hi> and one appointed for cariage of prouiſion in this iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, to make what way they poſſibly could for the <hi>Groyne,</hi> to commaund the ſaid ſhippes prouiſions and people, to meet him in the mouth of the harbour, thence to beare in his company for Saint <hi>Anderas.</hi> But the ſaid ſhippe was becalmed as was the reſt of the fleet likewiſe, and could make no way, but kept company with vs till Sunday morning; after which time we had no more ſight of her till her comming to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19287:9"/> the <hi>Groyne,</hi> which was the next day after our arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall there.</p>
            <p>On Munday morning earely the land was diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered by the fleet, and about fower of the clocke in the afternoone, they arriued into the road of the <hi>Groyne,</hi> being a very ſafe and pleaſant harbour.</p>
            <p>We were no ſooner deſcried from the lande; but the Gouernour of the towne <hi>Don Lewys de Carilla de Toledo; Seigneur Peynte Corde de Carazena,</hi> and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of <hi>Galicia,</hi> had commaunded to make ready for interteyning his Lordſhip, which was moſt royal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed, being vpon entrance into the harbour, firſt ſaluted from a fort on the North ſide the towne with twentie great peeces of Ordinance. Then from the fort lately builte vpon the rocke with ſixe and twentie peeces of great Ordinaunce; and from the towne and caſtle with thirtie great peeces of Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance at leaſt. His Lordſhip comming to ancor with the reſt of the ſhippes, gaue them their whole broad ſides. Immediatly vpon his Lordſhips arriuall, the Gouernour of the Towne ſent the foure princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall officers, Commanders of the Towne together with his Brother <hi>don Iohn de pacheco</hi> and <hi>Don Lewis de Carilla de Toledo</hi> his only ſonne to giue his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the welcome, wherein they demeand themſelues ſo exceeding kindly, and with the moſt affable and reſpectiue ſpeeches that might be, excuſing their ſlender entertainment by reaſon of their late vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of his Lordſhips comming to the <hi>Groyne,</hi> for that they had intelligence his Lordſhip meant to haue gone to Saint <hi>Anderas.</hi> After a ſhort time ſpent
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19287:10"/> in complement with theſe Commanders, the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour himſelfe (being accompanied with diuers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonages of worth came aboard in a barge which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to haue been made of purpoſe for this vſe. The Rowers and Mariners thereof (being clad in blew ſilke Caſſoks and Caps, and the barge couered with blew veluet, and newly painted) reported to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, that the King his maſter had eſpecially written to him in theſe words; That he ſhould haue reſpect, what perſon he was that was comen Ambaſſadour, from whom he was come, and to whom he was ſent; and this he ſhould do euery thing for the honour of theſe three perſons without ſparing any thing that might be fitte for his Lordſhips entertainment. And therefore the Gouernour intreated his Lordſhip to go on Land, which he refuſed to do that night, but being much importuned, he promiſed to go on ſhore the next day. During the Gouernours abode on the ſhip there came many on board likewiſe, and they of all conditions. Doctors of Law, Churchmen, Friers, and of all other ſorts of people; who all ſeemed much to wonder and admire the greatneſſe and neatneſſe of that Galeon as they termed her: exceedingly commending and applauding the ſame. At the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture of the ſaid Gouernour from the ſhippes, his Lordſhip gaue many pieces of ordinance, which were againe receaued and anſwered from the towne and forts. The whole towne indeed being but a hold and fort, but very ſtrong. That night they ſent from the towne vnto his Lordſhip a preſent of fiſh &amp; fruit, bread and ſuch like commodities as the country yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19287:10"/> excuſing that they were not able to ſhew their loue in better ſort vnto his Lordſhip: for that Munday the day of his arriuall being Saint <hi>Markes</hi> day with them, and the Fiſhermen as then not going to ſea, and alſo hauing feaſted as that day for ioy of the birth of the yong Prince: they were the more vnfurni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of better preſent and more fitte for his entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>On Tueſday the ſixtienth day of <hi>April,</hi> his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip prepared to go on ſhore, to his lodging, which was prepared for him at the gouernours houſe, which houſe is the whole pleaſure of the towne, for that it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlooketh the whole harbor and is ſeated in the heart of the towne. The gouernour likewiſe hauing taken great care to receiue his Lordſhip in the moſt honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable manner: and therefore had vpon intelligence of our comming to the <hi>Groyne,</hi> cauſed to be builded a bridge of Timber aboue forty yards long and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame, yellow red and blew, and garniſhed the ſame with many pencels of ſilke of like colours very formally and planted the way into the towne with bowes of Baies and Orange trees, and ſtrewed the ſame with ruſhes and flowers. The whole company of the towne and many more of the Country (being as was ſuppoſed) drawen thither for this purpoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, all ready to giue his Lorſhip entertainment after the beſt faſhion; when the time came that his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip might conueniently land, for vntill three of the clocke after noone the flood was not, vpon which he muſt of neceſſity land, the Gouernour ſent diuers of the Commanders of the town to giue notice, that he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19287:11"/> and other the Magiſtrates of the towne would attend vpon the bridge, his Lordſhip thereupon tooke his barge carying in the head therof, an Ancient of white ſilke, with the picture of the ſunne in the vpper part thereof; his <hi>Moto</hi> or word being <hi>Deſir Na' Repos,</hi> written in maner of a Beud, within the ſame, and ſo came in very honourable maner to the bridge, where ſtaied for him the ſaid Gouernor, Iudges and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of the towne, enterteining the Engliſh as they landed, the whileſt the muſicke, being Shagbots and Hoboyes &amp; placed for that purpoſe vpon the bridge, plaied ſweet and delectable melody, and ſo the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards intermingling themſelues with the Engliſh ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their degrees, euer giuing the right hand to the Engliſh, paſſed into the Towne in order as fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. Firſt went foure of his Lordſhips ſeruants, who were appointed Marſhals for his traine. After followed certaine of his officers in his houſe &amp; cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in their liueries. Next after followed the gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men his ſeruants and eſpeciall officers in their liueries of blacke veluet. Then followed the Eſquires and Knights euery one according to his degree: then with our Lords and Nobles, diuers Spaniſh Commanders and Iudges of the kingdome of <hi>Galicia.</hi> At their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the town, there was ſhot off an exceeding great volley of ſhot both great and ſmall, and ſo they paſſed all on foot to the Condies houſe, and at the entrance of his Lordſhip into the houſe, there were ſhot off a great number of Chambers, being for that purpoſe, as it ſhould ſeeme, planted ouer againſt the Condies gate. His Lordſhip being thus receiued was
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19287:11"/> exceedingly well appointed and lodged. That night what by reaſon of the littleneſſe of the roome and the muchneſſe of the company, he was both lated, and could not but be much troubled at his Supping, wherein the Cond and his officers, did make manifeſt their exceeding care and reſpect to haue all things to content his Lordſhip, and the company with ſo much attendance and obſeruance, as it was rather a trouble and offence to any well minded to ſee their extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary paines taken in ther ſeruice, than cauſe of excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in any wiſe, eſpecially for that it did appeare, There was prouided what the countrie could any way affoord.</p>
            <p>There his Lordſhip reſted from that time forward, ſometimes riding abroad to take the aire on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe, other times in his Carroch, &amp; euer with much applauſe and admiration of the people. So that it could not but giue him much contentment to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue how welcome he ſeemed generally to the whole country. In his paſſages abroad he tooke oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to ſhew his bounty to the poore, which in that place abound greatly, many of them being very miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable creatures to ſee, and wherewith his Lordſhip was in mercy &amp; charity much moued, not ſparing his purſe one houre in the day; for beſides what he gaue abroad, he neuer ſhewed himſelfe in his gallery but he prouided good ſummes of money to giue for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe of thoſe miſerable poore people, who indeeed during his abode there made little account of other li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing than of his reliefe.</p>
            <p>Whileſt we reſted in the <hi>Groyne</hi> a certaine mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19287:12"/> being one of the Repulſe, and hauing vpon Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſday the ſeuenteenth day of the preſent moneth of <hi>April</hi> brought on ſhore ſome company and ſtaying in Towne vntill amongſt lewd company he became tipled; that thereby he gaue offence in his behauiour, by violent ſtriking of one of the Churchmen of the towne, although it was not directly complained of by any, either of the Church or of the towne, yet by chance came to his Lordſhips knowledge, who for that he receaued ſuch extraordinary kind and liberall vſage both for himſelfe and his followers, and that generally from all, if no other cauſe might moue him but that, was much offended therewith, and therefore thought good to take due puniſhment of that ſo foule a fault, commanding that preſent inquiry ſhould be made through all the ſhippes; who of them had been on ſhore, at laſt finding the offendour, he committed him preſently to the Bibboes, there to remaine till the next day which was Friday, what time he appointed Sir <hi>Richard Lewſon,</hi> his Admirall and Marſhall to call vnto him the other Admiralls and Captaines of the fleete, and throughly to examine the offence and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly to proceed without any reſpect or fauour. They calling before them the ſaid offendour, and fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding indeed that the fellow was drunke and by no meanes could remember whether he had ſtroken the ſaid Churchman or no; &amp; although the maner of his ſtriking was ſo ſlight, and the party ſaid to be ſtroken ſo vile in reputation of the whole city, as they gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally pitied any man ſhould once be called in queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ſo baſe a perſon: the ſaid Commiſſioners and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19287:12"/> Iurie proceeded and finding him guilty of ſtriking the ſaid Churchman, being contrary to Law and his Lordſhips former decrees in that behalfe, adiudged him to be preſently hanged. Heere it is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood that the matter could not be ſo priuately caried but many of the Towne and ſome Churchmen alſo, had made meanes to get aboard and ſaw the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſo auſtere &amp; reſolute, that preſently they ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Conde &amp; the Honourable Condeſſe his wife vpon any condition to hinder the execution. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, when the Conde, but eſpecially the Condeſſe and her daughter had taken notice, they neuer left intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Lordſhip to recall his auerred ſentence and iudgement: and which to do his Lordſhip could not without offering much vnkindneſſe refuſe or denie. Many reaſons were alleadged by the Conde and the Condeſſe, that the party offended was a man vile in reputation and eſteemed as a man halfe Lunatike, that the offence was not a malicious or determinate wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful offence, and therefore, the premiſſes conſidered, his Lordſhip could not but with more iudgement paſſe it ouer, than ſo ſeuerely proſecute the execution of Iuſtice vpon ſo mean a cauſe, eſpecially ſithence no information or complaint was by the party offended, or by any other of the Court proſecuted on his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. His Lordſhip thus vrged, granted he ſhould be deliuered vnto the Conde, to be vſed as he thought good, &amp; therefore commanded he ſhould be brought on land and deliuered vnto him, which was done, one of the Maſters going along with him, the Boat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon leading him with a halter about his necke, who
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19287:13"/> when he came before the Conde, fel on his knees, and would haue made much proteſtation, but the Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Conde, tooke him vp, tooke off the halter fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his necke, and commanded him to be carried to eat in the Buttery, for that the dolefull lookes of the man, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued much pity in the Conde.</p>
            <p>On Tueſday the foure and twentieth day of <hi>April,</hi> according to the computation of <hi>England,</hi> his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſolemnized the feaſt of Saint <hi>George,</hi> which was done in very ſolemne maner, and with the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard for that the towneſmen taking notice of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment to feaſt, came in troupes, to ſee and obſerue the faſhions of <hi>England:</hi> his Lordſhip therefore ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing deſired ſufferance of the Conde, to vſe his owne officers for that day, appointed to be ſerued after the faſhion of <hi>England,</hi> both in ſeruice and diet. And wheras the Conde had for his Lordſhips ſtate, ſet vp a cloth of Eſtate with his proper armes, his Lordſhip commanded to ſet vp a ſtate of his owne being rich of Bawdkim, without armes, other then the armes of his Highneſſe with S. <hi>Georges</hi> croſſe, as is the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, his owne armes was placed a good diſtance off vpon the hangings, and on the right hand of the cloth of Eſtate, for that both the roome was moſt conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent as alſo it was thought the Conde would haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his Lordſhip, as he was deſired. After pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate praiers in his chamber, and that moſt of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany was come to him, &amp; dinner being ſerued in ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, his Lordſhip came forth in his robes of S. <hi>George,</hi> to meet the Conde. But the Conde fearing to do any thing that might impeach the honour of his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19287:13"/> Maſter or be preſent there to heare any thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, which might offend him in reſpect of the honour of his Maſter, after that he had ſtaied to ſee his Lordſhip waſh and ſet at the Table praied leaue and ſo went to his priuate lodging. At the comming in of the ſecond courſe, according to the faſhion of <hi>England,</hi> the Kings ſtile was proclaimed in three ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall languages by <hi>Somerſett</hi> herauld crying, Largeſſe, who had a liberall reward for the ſame. And ſo his Lordſhip being ſerued very honourably by perſons of the better ſort, and very richly in diet and in plate, ended his dinner, ſitting alone at the table, but diuers other Lords, Knights and Eſquires ſitting in the ſame roome at two other tables by.</p>
            <p>After dinner, the Conde came to congratulate his Lordſhip ſeeming much to repent him, that he kept not him co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany at dinner, ſithence he had vnderſtood by his brother (who ſtood all dinner time there, and well obſeruing all) that there was not any thing, that might giue the leaſt cauſe of offence or exception. Therfore the Conde diſcouered that he much deſired to keepe him company at Supper, which he did, his Lordſhip ſitting as he did at dinner, vnder the esko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheon of his own armes, the Conde on the ſame ſide but on the left hand the cloth of Eſtate and at the lower end of the table. Whileſt they ſate at Supper, much company came in to ſee them, diuers Ladies and other Gentlemen of the better ſort comming priuately to obſerue the faſhion of our ſtate, which his Lordſhip performed moſt honourably and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to the glory of our nation, and to no ſmall honour
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19287:14"/> of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday, the foure and twentieth day of the ſaid moneth of <hi>April</hi> about noone, there came a gentleman from the Court, who gaue notice to the Conde and his Lordſhip, that, that night <hi>Don Blaſco de Aragon</hi> nephew to the Duke of <hi>Terra noua:</hi> one that had been formerly in <hi>England</hi> with the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble would be there, who indeed about ſeuen of the clocke that night, came accordingly, to ſalute his Lordſhip from the King his maſter, and to giue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding both of the preparation for his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and his company vpon the way as alſo what or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhould be preſently taken, for their more ſpeedie Iourney.</p>
            <p>Tueſday, the thirtieth of <hi>April,</hi> there was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Communion on ſhipboord, to the which reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted diuers Knights and Gentlemen, and as many as could conueniently come to the ſame.</p>
            <p>On Wedneſday &amp; Thurſday his Lordſhip treated with the Conde, the ſaide <hi>Don Blaſco</hi> and <hi>Don Iaſpar de Bullion</hi> the <hi>Apoſentador,</hi> Mayor to the King, which ſaide <hi>Iaſpar de Bullion</hi> was lately come from the Court of purpoſe to prouide for his Lordſhip and his traine with commiſſion from the King to ſee them furniſhed of all neceſſaries for their Iourneying.</p>
            <p>In this conference (notwithſtanding it had beene formerly vnderſtood, there ſhould be no want of meanes or neceſſaries, for his Lordſhip and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their iourney to Court) it appeared that the company being numbred by the pole to be 650. per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of all ſorts, beſides their carriages which were
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19287:14"/> very many: the country could by no meanes ſupply the whole number: therefore it was thought good to leſſen them, as much as conueniently they might, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluing to leaue diuers of his Lordſhips owne people abord the ſhips, till they returne: ſome alſo were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatched for <hi>England,</hi> with the Carroches, Litters and Mares, and ſuch other his furniture, as by <hi>Don Blaſco</hi> was vnderſtood he ſhould haue little vſe of. And for that, beſides riding mules we vnderſtood there were ſent thither by the King foure litters, and foure coches which ſtaied for vs at <hi>villa Franca,</hi> for the more eaſe of his Lordſhip when he pleaſed and for thereliefe of any Gentleman that might happen to be ſicke vpon the way, which in ſo long and tedious a iourney was likely to be. And indeed as it happened moſt of them were put to vſe, one coch and one litter being appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for his Lordſhips owne vſe, another coch and litter appointed to the Ambaſſadour-Leager, and the other ſeruing ſometimes one and ſometimes another, as occaſion ſerued and they deſired.</p>
            <p>Thurſday the ſecond day of <hi>May,</hi> there was prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the market place, a certaine peece of ground railed in ſquare the ſpace of twenty yeards or more, with Scaffolds, built of purpoſe about the ſame: wherein the Engliſh were very ſufficiently appointed and placed, for the ſeeing of theſe ſports. His Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and other the Noblemen were placed in ſeuerall windowes, in a very faire roome in the Kings State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, being for that purpoſe hanged with rich Arras and ſeuerall clothes of Eſtate ouer the windowes, on the wall on the outſide the houſe: they being come
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19287:15"/> to their ſtandings, the Ladies and better ſort of the towne being likewiſe placed in a conuenient roome for that purpoſe, they began their ſports after this maner. Firſt, there was brought in a caſtle wherein a Lady was encloſed, and kept by foure monſters. The ſaid caſtle being placed in the middeſt of the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, there appeared foure Knights armed, with their Pages going before them with Drums and Fife play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: who preſently aſſailed the caſtle, ſurprized the monſters, relieued the Lady and ſo ſet fire of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle. This deuiſe being, as we vnderſtood of it, as much to ſhew the ſtrangeneſſe of the fire works, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed were many, as for any other reaſon which we obſerued by the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Theſe repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the iudgement of <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </note>Then came <hi>Venus, Pallas, Iuno, Cupid</hi> euery one led ſeuerally by Sauages, after whom followed foure other armed Knights, in colours painted blew and white. Then came a third company being foure in number, in coloured armours likewiſe, with croſſes on their breaſts in ſhew like knights of <hi>Matta,</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in with them a chariot wherein the chiefe ſate <hi>Peace, Plenty</hi> and other vertues, being likewiſe plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſame: with their ſeuerall names written on their backes. After whom likewiſe followed foure o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knightes armed, with trumpets ſounding. When they had all appeared, they fell to Barriers according to the direction of certaine Gentlemen appointed to marſhall the ſame. Some of our Engliſh Lords and Knights being intreated by the Spaniards to aſſiſt them therein alſo: they encountered one another ſingle firſt by two, after increaſing their number ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19287:15"/> to the pleaſure of the Iudges and Marſhals; when they had broken their ſtaues (or at leaſt done their beſt to breake them) retiring, fell to it againe with their ſwords, according to the maner of Barriers, fiue blows a peece. In a Scaffold directly oppoſite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the place, wherein the Lords ſtood, ſate the Iudges of theſe ſports amongſt whom the Lord <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> of <hi>Effingham</hi> was intreated by the Magiſtrates of the towne to be one, which Iudges vpon euery en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter gaue reward to the beſt deſeruer: as Scarfes, Gloues, Choppimors, Ribbens, and ſuch like which were by the Knights thankefully receaued, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed as fauoures vpon their miſtreſſes; at laſt the Knights encountered <hi>pell mell,</hi> one another; and as it ſeemed in a very furious maner. But the Barre being made in faſhion like a trough, and many fire works being cunningly contriued in the ſame, and duely tooke fire, and ſo with flame and ſmoake they were parted.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſports ended, there was a banquet caried vp to his Lordſhip &amp; other the Lords and Ladies which were in another roome next adioining, being indeed both plentifull and coſtly, and ſerued in by the chiefe Gentleman of the Country and Towne. The ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet ended, and night comming on there were brought into the ſame place diuers fire works: one in the faſhion of a Chariot, another like the wheele of Fortune, another like a Caſtle, and ſuch like garded and attended with diuers wild men, with clubbes and wheeles, with ſeuerall fire works: men riding with ſpeares in their hands all conteining ſquibbes and fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19287:16"/> with which they ranne at one another, as in maner of Tilt. The diuerſities of the fire workes were many, and for the ſtrangeneſſe and maner of perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance thereof, generally commended and ſo well liked as two houres ſpent in that paſtime ſeemed but a moment.</p>
            <p>Friday the third day of <hi>May</hi> his Lordſhip hauing his company furniſhed, with conuenient Mules for riding, as alſo for cariage of their trunks and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, about eleuen of the cloke accompanied with the Gouernour and other the Magiſtrates of the towne, ſet forward on his iourney. <hi>Don Blaſco de Aragon,</hi> and <hi>Don Iaſpar de Bullion</hi> the chiefe Herbenger for the King, accompanying his Lordſhip for the purpoſes aforeſaied: in the paſſage from the towne the waits and ſhagbots were placed playing all the while; at our departing from the towne and our leaue taking of the Gouernour, they gaue a ſmall volley of ſhot out of the towne. His Lordſhip being halfe a mile out of the towne and yet within ſight of the ſhips as they lay at Road, the ſaid ſhippes tooke their leaue alſo of vs with many peece of ordinance.</p>
            <p>The ſaid Gouernour, as before is mentioned is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Don Lewis, de Carilla de Toledo &amp;c.</hi> and is of the countrie of <hi>Caſtilla,</hi> but appointed heere by the King as Gouernour of the <hi>Groyn</hi> and all the country of <hi>Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licia:</hi> a man of very mild and affable behauiour, very curteous and moſt reſpectiue of the Engliſh in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, as by the great care and good vſage of vs whileſt we lodged in the <hi>Groyn</hi> appeared.</p>
            <p>That night being as is aforeſaied the third day of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19287:16"/> 
               <hi>May,</hi> according to the computation of <hi>England</hi> we rode to <hi>Bytaunce,</hi> being diſtant three leagues from the <hi>Groyn,</hi> where his Lordſhip and his company were well entertained and lodged.</p>
            <p>Saterday the fourth day of <hi>May,</hi> we rode from <hi>By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce</hi> to a certaine town called <hi>Villa Alua,</hi> 6. leagues, where our entertainment was ſuch as the towne could affoord, by reaſon of the meanes thereof.</p>
            <p>Sunday the fifth day of <hi>May</hi> we rode forward to a very faire towne called <hi>Lugo,</hi> being diſtant from <hi>Villa Alua</hi> ſeuen leagues. The Alcaylde and other officers of the town, meeting his Lordſhip about halfe a mile without the gates, and accompanying vs into the towne, the ſtreets being decked with bowes and the wals of their houſes garniſhed with their beſt hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and furniture. In the way comming thither his Lordſhip receaued letters of intelligence and congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulations from the Conde at the <hi>Groyne,</hi> which he accepted very kindly.</p>
            <p>The meſſenger being diſpatched from <hi>Lugo,</hi> and rewarded with a chaine of Gold of good value: on Munday we rode to a certaine towne called <hi>Terra Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtella</hi> diſtant from <hi>Lugo</hi> eight leagues.</p>
            <p>Tueſday the ſeuenth day of <hi>May,</hi> we trauelled all the morning vp to a high mountaine by the ſpace of ſix leagues, and dined at a litle village called <hi>çebrera,</hi> where we receiued ſuch intertainme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnexpected, as was altogether in an arbor of green bowes made of purpoſe of ſuch a conuenient length, that that recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued his Lordſhip and all the better ſort of his traine. And after dinner we rode to a certaine towne called
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19287:17"/> 
               <hi>Villa Franca,</hi> being diſtant ſix leagues, where his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was receaued with the towneſmen, the ſtreets by all the way where we paſſed being garniſhed with bowes and ſtrewed with hearbs and flowers: muſicke being likewiſe placed neere the houſe where his Lordſhip ſhould lodge.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday for that the company were ſomewhat weary, his Lordſhip diſpoſed himſelfe to reſt: chiefly, for that the Ambaſſadour Leadger complained of ſickeneſſe, as alſo to relieue the Mules, forbearing to trauell in ſo foule weather as it fell out to be the ſame day.</p>
            <p>Thurſday the ninth day of <hi>May</hi> we rode by a town called <hi>Conguſta,</hi> to <hi>Beubibre,</hi> to bed, where his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was lodged in a caſtle of the Conde <hi>de Alualiſta,</hi> but very old and meane. The towne being ſo poore and men alſo, as if the officers of his Highneſſe, had not then, as indeed they did, taken more than ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary paines and care, it had not been poſſible to haue lodged halfe the Company.</p>
            <p>Friday the tenth day of <hi>May,</hi> we came to <hi>Aſtorga</hi> being a city walled and ſtanding in a pleaſant and champion country, and conteining in it many Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, amongſt which one is a Cathedrall, two Frie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and two Noneries. A mile without the towne we were met with the Alcayldy and Officers of the towne, ouer the gates hung diuers guidons and ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſilke: one of them being a large white banner of Damaske, in faſhion of a Guydon and placed in the middeſt of the reſt. Muſicke likewiſe playing all the way as we paſſed, the houſes garniſhed with their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19287:17"/> beſt hangings, and the ſtreets ſtrewed with hearbs and flowers.</p>
            <p>Saturday the eleuenth day of <hi>May</hi> his Lordſhip hauing had vnderſtanding of the faireneſſe of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle there belonging to the <hi>Marqueſſ</hi> of <hi>Aſtorga,</hi> and being deſired by <hi>Don Blaſco</hi> to take view thereof, in paſſing out of the towne, alighted to ſee the ſame: the houſe indeed being a very ſtrong caſtle and hauing in it a very faire gallery with many goodly pictures and pieces of painting both large and coſtly, and alſo a rich library with many fine rarities in the ſame. After riding foure leagues to a certaine towne called <hi>La Ban'eſa,</hi> where in the way comming we were mette with diuers Gypſies (as they termed them) men and women dauncing and tumbling much after the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſco faſhion, continued till we came to the towne.</p>
            <p>Sunday the twelfth day of <hi>May</hi> we rode eight leagues to a towne called <hi>Benavente,</hi> where a mile without the towne Alcaylde &amp; chiefe Officers of the towne met vs: bringing with them a company of Gypſies likewiſe, ſinging and dauncing, playing and ſhewing diuers feats of actiuity: conducting his Lordſhip to the Conde of <hi>Benevante</hi> his houſe where he lodged that night.</p>
            <p>Munday we rode forward eight leagues, to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine towne called <hi>Villa Garcia,</hi> where we were recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with a morriſe daunce of certaine comely gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, being in number eight, as alſo with eight Boyes attired like Satyres or Shepheards with Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards hookes, who as they daunced plaied with the ſame after the faſhion of <hi>Mattachyna.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:19287:18"/>
            <p>In this Towne is a very faire Colledge wherein is only taught the rules of <hi>Grammar,</hi> and grounds of the Latine tongue. It conteineth about 600. Scholers: the Church a very faire Church, very richly ſet out with many goodly peeces of painting: the Altar and Quier exceeding rich and faire. From hence his Lordſhip receaued order by the Kings officers to go to a certaine towne called <hi>Simancas,</hi> which though it was rather further in diſtance than <hi>Valladolid,</hi> yet for that his Lordſhip ſhould not come late nor his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany ouer-wearied, this towne was appointed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him before our comming to the Court. Other reaſons were giuen, that is, in the right way between <hi>Villa Garcia</hi> and <hi>Valladolid,</hi> a bridge was lately bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, whereby of neceſſity we muſt haue paſſed; and alſo that the King deſired we ſhould enter through the high ſtreet and the beſt part of the towne, which we did: and therefore appointed our way by <hi>Cimancas.</hi> Accordingly we came to <hi>Simancas</hi> on Tueſday at night ſomewhat late, being ouertaken with extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary foule weather, and greatlie annoyed with the ſame.</p>
            <p>In the way between <hi>Villa Garcia</hi> and <hi>Simancas</hi> we paſſed by a very faire monaſtery of Monkes of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of S. <hi>Benedick,</hi> being not long ſithence builded, but exceeding faire and rich: whereunto there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing incloſed as much ground, as the wal thereof, being of ſtone, is in circuit, a league, or better: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in which is all kind of game royall as Pheſants, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tridges, Hares, Conies and ſuch like. The Church heere is very curiouſly and workemanly built, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19287:18"/> garniſhed with many curious peeces of painting, with Copes very rich, and very curiouſly wrought.</p>
            <p>That night at Supper, his Lordſhip had notice, that it was the Kings pleaſure, we ſhould reſt at <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancas</hi> all Wedneſday, and not till Thurſday come to the Court.</p>
            <p>On Wedneſday after dinner, there came from the Court <hi>Don Iuan de Suniga</hi> eldeſt ſonne to the Conde <hi>de Villa mediana</hi> Ambaſſadour in <hi>England:</hi> as alſo <hi>Don Pedro de Taſsis</hi> the new appointed Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour for <hi>England,</hi> accompanied with diuers others, who hauing congratulated his Lordſhip, ſtaying with him ſome halfe houre or there abouts, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted.</p>
            <p>That night we vnderſtood that it was the Kings pleaſure, his Lordſhip ſhould come to Court on Thurſday, whereupon euery one taking notice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of made preparation accordingly.</p>
            <p>Thurſday being the ſixteenth day of <hi>May,</hi> we ſtaid till after dinner expecting to receaue more particular directions from Court, at which time there came to attend his Lordſhip thither. The marqueſſe of <hi>Came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſſa, Don Pedro de Suniga, Don Iuan de Taſsis, Don Blaſco de Aragon,</hi> and diuers other Knights and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of the Kings houſe and chamber, bringing with them diuers coches, ſo that his Lordſhip was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by <hi>Don Blaſco,</hi> and the Marqueſſe in the firſt coch; the Ambaſſadour Leager, by ſome others in the ſecond; other Knights and Gentlemen filling aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well the other coches, which came along from the <hi>Groyne,</hi> as thoſe which were brought from Court by
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19287:19"/> theſe Lords. After we had trauelled about foure En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh miles (for from <hi>Cimancas</hi> to the Court it was accounted but ſix) and hauing been met with many of the better ſort, in their coches, his Lordſhip was moued by <hi>Don Blaſco</hi> and the reſt, to go into a certain banquetting houſe which ſtood vpon the high way, to ſee the delicacy of the orchards and gardens, as to taſt of the variety of fruits within the ſame. But we rather ſuppoſe to make ſtay for ſuch Nobles as were appointed by the King to giue meeting to his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and were not as then come forward. During his Lordſhips ſtay in this garden there was a horſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto him from the King, which the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe did vſe to ride on. After they had ſtaied there by the ſpace of a long houre or more, there came from the Towne diuers Noblemen, the chiefe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was, the Duke of <hi>Fryas</hi> Conſtable of <hi>Caſtilla,</hi> the Kings late Ambaſſadour in <hi>England:</hi> the Duke of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fantaſgo:</hi> the Duke of <hi>Alberquerques:</hi> the Duke of <hi>Cea:</hi> the Duke of <hi>Seſa:</hi> the Duke of <hi>Paſtraua:</hi> The Marqueſſe of <hi>S. German:</hi> the Conde of <hi>Chincou:</hi> the Conde of <hi>Punion en Roſtro:</hi> the Marq. <hi>de Lauaneſſa:</hi> the Conde of <hi>Aguyllar:</hi> the Conde <hi>de Beroſa:</hi> the Conde <hi>de Nieua:</hi> the Conde <hi>de Cornua:</hi> the Conde <hi>de Paredes:</hi> the Conde <hi>de Lodoſa:</hi> the Marqueſſe <hi>del Carpio:</hi> the Marqueſſods <hi>Tauera:</hi> the Marqueſſ <hi>de Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la Nueua:</hi> the Conde <hi>Apala:</hi> Conde <hi>de Salinas:</hi> Marq. <hi>de Ceralua:</hi> Marq. <hi>de Fuentes:</hi> Marq. <hi>de Alcaneſ:</hi> Conde <hi>de Galues,</hi> the Admirall of <hi>Aragon,</hi> and many other Lords and Knights in great number. His Lordſhip ſetting forward in very good order, accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19287:19"/> with a great multitude of Nobles, Knights and Gentlemen, as afore is ſaied. The weather being all that time extraordinarily hot, ſuddenly to the great diſordering of all the company, there fell ſo great a ſhewer of raine as the like was not ſeene of long time before: and continuing till the company could get to the towne, notwithſtanding which his Lordſhip kept ſtill his horſe backe, accompanied with many of the chiefe of the company, and riding for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to his appointed lodging, which was in a very faire houſe of the Conde of <hi>Salinas,</hi> and not farre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant from the Court; an infinite number of people, 800. coches filled with Ladies were gotten out of the towne to meet and ſee his Lordſhip and his compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, all which tooke part of this great ſhewer to their no little diſcomfort.</p>
            <p>The order of our going into the towne was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed as followeth: Firſt rode two Trumpets, all the ſumpter and carriages being about two houres before ſent into the towne: after whom followed certaine Gentlemen ſeruants to the Knights and Lords, as alſo the Leadger Ambaſſadours ſeruants in liueries very faire to the number of ſixty. Then followed ſix Trumpeters of his Lordſhips in ſuits of Damaske holding their Trumpets in their hands, but not ſounding. Then came diuers Gentlemen of good ſort, with whom alſo followed his Lordſhips Gentlemen and principall Officers in their Liueries of blacke veluet to the number of thirty. Then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Eſquires, Knights and Lords euery one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their degree, being accompanied with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19287:20"/> ſeuerall Spaniſh Knights and Lords; after whom came his Lordſhip accompanied with the Nobles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned; which order, for that the raine fell ſo exceedingly, could not be continued as was ment, but by reaſon thereof, diuers made what haſt they could to their lodging; and yet were throughly wet before they could get thither. His Lordſhip accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied as afore and entring into the towne at the Gate called <hi>La Puerta del Campo,</hi> paſſed through the chiefe parts of the towne and along by the Court gate. The King, Queen and Ladies (as it was ſa d) ſtanding in ſeuerall windowes to take view of the company; about ſix of the clocke came to the place appointed for his Lordſhips lodging.</p>
            <p>That night came diuers Noble men as alſo the <hi>Mayordomo</hi> to the Queen to viſit his Lordſhip from her Highneſſe, which was much wondred at by the Spaniards themſelues, for that (if they ſpeake true) they neuer knew the like fauour done to any Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour whatſoeuer.</p>
            <p>The next day being Friday the ſeuenteenth day of <hi>May,</hi> there came to viſit his Lordſhip the Duke of <hi>Lerma, Don Franciſco Gouees de Sandoual &amp;c.</hi> a man of eſpeciall regard and account with the King, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with diuers Dukes and Condes.</p>
            <p>Thither alſo that day came the Duke of <hi>Medyna de Ryoſeco,</hi> a youth of ten yeares of age, Admirall of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilla</hi> by inheritance, accompanied with diuers other Lords and men of great account.</p>
            <p>Vpon Saterday the eighteenth day of <hi>May</hi> in the morning the King ſent the Conde <hi>d' Guklues,</hi> and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19287:20"/> diuers others of his Priuy chamber to viſit his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the ſame day.</p>
            <p>The firſt audience ſomewhat before dinner; his Lordſhip had intelligence that the Kings Maieſty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to giue him audience in the after noone; whereof the Engliſh Lords, Knights and Gentlemen taking notice prepared themſelues to giue their at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, although not in ſo good faſhion as they deſired, &amp; would, had they had vnderſtanding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ouer night: his Lordſhip therefore ſtaying his Highneſſe pleaſure, about three of the clocke in the after noone.</p>
            <p>The Conſtable accompanied with twenty No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemen or more, whereof three or foure of them were of the Grandes of <hi>Spaine;</hi> and diuers other men of dignity and eſteeme in the Court, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them many coches, came to conduct his Lordſhip and the company to the Court; many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were gathered in the ſtreets to ſee the paſſage of his Lordſhip &amp; his company. The number of the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches was about twenty; but notwithſtanding many of our Noblemen and Knights rode vpon their rich footeclothes, the Kings guard waited euen from the vttermoſt gate of the Pallace to the Preſence cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber dore, being all newly ſuited in colloured veluet yellow &amp; red, but in ſeuerall habits; that thereby they might be the better diſtinguiſhed being in number 300. whereof there are 100. Swiſſers, 100. Spaniſh horſemen, and 100. Wallons. At the Pallace gate ſtood diuers Noble men, Knights and Gentlemen, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom was the Duke of <hi>Infantaſgo,</hi> the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19287:21"/> of <hi>Vellada,</hi> and others all appointed to receaue and giue his Lordſhip entertainment, and to conduct and guide the company vp into the Preſence, where the King ſate vnder a rich cloth of Eſtate, and by him ſtood eight Grandes of <hi>Spaine</hi> couered.<note place="margin">It is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for any to ſtand coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the preſence of the King, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he be a Grande.</note> The care theſe Lords tooke to giue contentment to the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh was ſo great, that we might eaſily perceiue, they ſpared not to put out of the ſaide roome all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of people of what condition ſoeuer, of purpoſe to make way, and giue place euen to the meaneſt of the Engliſh, which would preſſe in to ſee the King, not keeping out any of how meane condition ſoeuer.</p>
            <p>His Lordſhip hauing deliuered his mind in Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the mouth of Maſter <hi>Gyles Porter</hi> his Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as alſo the Kings Maieſties Letters into his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe owne hands: the King deſcending from his chaire gaue intertainment to his Lordſhip with moſt kind and affable behauiour, appointing him to ſitte downe by him and that very neere, which eſpeciall fauour was much obſerued, and reported as a thing neuer vſed to any Ambaſſadour before that time. Some ſhort time ſpent in conference with his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, his Highneſſe was pleaſed to take notice of ſuch Nobles and Gentlemen, as accompanied his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in this his long and painfull iourney: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon required they ſhould draw neere, which they did, each after other, to do their reuerence, and, as they ſay, <hi>Beſar las manos,</hi> which was only in bowing low to the ground, without touching either hand or foot, or any other part of his garments: this done his
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19287:21"/> Lordſhip tooke his leaue, and the King appointed the Conſtable and others to conduct his Lordſhip and company to the Queenes ſide: where in a very faire preſence, ſate her Highneſſe with the <hi>Infanta</hi> by her, vnder a rich cloth of Eſtate, accompanied with many Ladies and Maides of Honour, diuided on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide the ſame roome, a good diſtance each from other, ſtanding cloſe by the wall, almoſt from one end of the chamber to the other. The Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Knights and Lords going along and before his Lordſhippe, were receiued by the <hi>Mayor do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo</hi> to the Queene, and ſo conducted to her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            <p>After ſome conference and complement his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip taking leaue of her Maieſty, for that it began to be late, all the Lords, Knights and Gentlemen, were called vp to the Queen, as formerly they had been to the King, euery one after other bowing himſelfe in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyſance and kiſſing the skirt of her Highneſſe kirtle departed: being conducted by the ſaid Dukes and Lords which both brought them to the Court and accompanied them backe againe to his lodging.</p>
            <p>Sunday, the nineteenth day of <hi>May,</hi> the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty went in proceſſion, firſt going into the Church neere the Pallace called Saint <hi>Paules,</hi> &amp; after through the towne to a Church called Saint <hi>Maries;</hi> in maner as followeth:</p>
            <p>Firſt went many Friers ſinging, bearing amongſt them diuers croſſes, banners, and other ceremonious reliques of the Church, the Sacrament being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe caried by foure church-officers.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:19287:22"/>
            <p>Then followed diuers Noblemen according to their degrees.</p>
            <p>Next before the Kings owne perſon went the yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the Princes of <hi>Sauoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then the king himſelfe in perſon: after whom fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Cardinal being Archbiſhop of <hi>Toledo,</hi> and with him the Prince of <hi>Sauoy</hi> the elder brother. Then followed together, the Prince of <hi>Moroco,</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Ambaſſadour: the Ambaſſadour of <hi>France:</hi> the Ambaſſadour of <hi>Venice:</hi> after whom followed diuers Gentlemen of the Kings chamber, and the reſt of the traine. After dinner there was preparation made for the chriſtening of the Prince, and for that the Court ſtood from the Church, there was ſet vp of purpoſe, for a more cloſe and conuenient paſſage, a very large Scaffold adioining to the end of a long Gallery, and to the Church likewiſe, the timber whereof was all couered with cloth of Gold very rich, and the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold being high was a good meanes to giue ſight to all the people. The manner of their comming to Church was in this ſort: The Kings Trumpets were placed neere and before the Church, in ſeuerall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, alwaies ſounding and one anſwering other: about foure of the clocke in the after noone, there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, deſcending by the Scaffold afore mentioned, to go into the Church of S. <hi>Paules,</hi> which, as is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaid, adioining to the ſcaffold; the Knights, Lords and Grandes going before: and ſome Dukes of eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall name, bearing diuers ceremonies likewiſe; as the <hi>Salera</hi> or <hi>Salt</hi> borne by one, the Taper of wax by another, the Chriſome by another: then the Crown
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19287:22"/> borne by the Conſtable, before whom went the King of Armes. The Prince was borne by the Duke of <hi>Lerma,</hi> in his armes; but tied to him with a rich ſcarfe or Band: he was aſſiſted by the Prince of <hi>Sauoy</hi> and the Conde of <hi>Miranda.</hi> Then followed the Infanta in a chaire as it ſhould ſeeme made for that purpoſe, and borne by diuers Gentlemen of the Kings bed and Priuy chamber, on their ſhoulders, aſſiſted by the yonger Prince of <hi>Sauoy.</hi> At the Church doore the Cardinal ſtaied for them in his Pontificalibus accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with three Biſhops and other eſpeciall officers of the Church: the ſinging men going before, and ſo conducting them to the Font, which was richly prepared and couered with a Canapy of cloth of gold; the Cardinall performed all the ceremonies ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the order of their Church, and ſo with Church muſicke, noiſe of Trumpets and many other wind Inſtruments they finiſhed their ceremonies, returning in ſuch maner as they went, being accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied alſo with moſt of the great Ladies of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and thoſe of the Court.</p>
            <p>He was Chriſtened <hi>Phillippe Domingo Victor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Godfather was the elder Prince of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> of whom he tooke his name, <hi>Victor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Godmother was the <hi>Infanta</hi> his Siſter.</p>
            <p>His Lordſhip was placed conueniently in the houſe of the Conde <hi>d' Rubadauia,</hi> in the morning, both to ſee the proceſſion, as alſo the going of the Prince to Chriſtening. But ſo ſoone as they were paſſed by, he with ſome other were priuately con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueied through a gallery on the backeſide of a Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19287:23"/> into the Church, into a place appointed of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for him and the Lords that were of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany.</p>
            <p>On Munday in the after noone the Ambaſſadour Leadger was by his Lordſhip preſented to the King, and by him gratiouſly receaued and allowed. That day in the after noone, came diuers Ambaſſadours to viſit his Lordſhip: as firſt, <hi>Don Franciſco de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchite</hi> Ambaſſadour for the ſtate of <hi>Venice;</hi> as alſo the French Ambaſſadour, <hi>Monſieur Baron de Barault Cheualier,</hi> who after ſome ſhort ſtay departed. At the time of the French Ambaſſadours being there, came likewiſe the Ambaſſadour reſiaunt for the Emperour. His Lordſhip euer ſhewing much affability and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie and accompanying them on their way to their coches with kind behauiour of his, being greatly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, cauſed an extraordinary reſpect and an excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding loue of all men towards him.</p>
            <p>That night alſo came to viſit his Lordſhip the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall of <hi>Toledo:</hi> being a very ſtately Prelate, well di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended, very rich, in his cariage very curteous; and in his expence liberall, as by the apparelling of his pages and ſeruants, and by his rich Sumpter cloths, hangings and ſuch like might well appeare.</p>
            <p>Tueſday, the one and twentieth of May, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip was conducted by <hi>Don Blaſco</hi> vnto the church called <hi>S. Maries,</hi> to ſee the ceremony and ſtate of the Queenes churching, whither the King and Queene came together; the King riding on horſebacke, the Queene in a very rich chariot of cloth of gold drawen by foure horſes all trapped and harneſſed with cloth
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19287:23"/> of golde: in which chariot likewiſe ſat the <hi>Infanta.</hi> Next followed in another chariot, the yoong Prince in the armes of an ancient Ladie. After followed two other caroches of blacke veluet, wherein ſat diuers Ducheſſes, Counteſſes, and other great perſonages, widowes.</p>
            <p>Then followed foure other caroches, all of one fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, wherein ſat ſeueral Ladies the Queenes Maids.</p>
            <p>This was the firſt day of the Queens going abroad, and as we accounted of it, her Churching day.</p>
            <p>This day his Lordſhip was inuited to dinner to the Conſtables, where he was accompanied by the Duke of <hi>Alberquerque,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Ceſa,</hi> and others. The maner of feaſting being not vſuall in <hi>Spaine,</hi> and our company being many, could not all receiue that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment which the Conſtable deſired to giue in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall. For the countrey conſidered, it is much to be maruelled, how they could do what they did; but it plainly appeared, nothing was left vndone for want of coſt, and that all preparation was made that the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey could any way affoord for their enterteinment.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday his Lordſhip was viſited by the <hi>Conde de Lemos,</hi> accompanied with diuers Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and men of good quality.</p>
            <p>That day likewiſe, and Thurſday, his Lordſhip vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited aſwell the Ambaſſadors afore mentioned, as alſo diuers other Lords and Ladies in the towne.</p>
            <p>Friday, the foure and twentieth day of May, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Knoell</hi> Eſquire, his Highneſſe ſeruant and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger for the deliuerie of certaine Preſents to the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> expecting and attending the Kings
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19287:24"/> pleaſure therein, was ſent for by <hi>Don Blaſco</hi> to come and bring the ſayd Preſents into a priuate Garden be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the Duke of <hi>Lerma,</hi> where the King and Queene came in perſon to receiue the ſame. The Preſents were ſix Horſes (three for the King, and three for the Queene) with ſaddles and clothes very richly imbroidered and coſtly; two Crosbowes with ſheifs of Arrowes; foure Fowling-pieces, with their furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, all very richly garniſhed and inlayed with fine plate of golde; and one couple of Lime hounds of an extraordinary goodneſſe. Which Preſents were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptably receiued; the King and Queene very much obſeruing and admiring the richneſſe and faſhion thereof.</p>
            <p>On Saturday the fiue and twentieth day of May, there came to viſit his Lordſhip the Biſhop <hi>Salustius Taernſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Montepolitan</hi> in <hi>Hetruria,</hi> and Ambaſſador for the Duke of <hi>Florence.</hi> After dinner came likewiſe to viſit his Lordſhip <hi>D. Iuan de Bourch</hi> Conde <hi>de Figaroa,</hi> Preſident of <hi>Portugall,</hi> with his foure ſonnes. That day alſo came to viſit him, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Conſtable, the Conde <hi>de Oliuares</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with diuers Marqueſſes and Earles. This Conde was one of them that was in <hi>England</hi> in the time of Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> The ſame day in the afternoon his Lordſhip viſited the Queen and deliuered her a faire rich Iewell as a token from the Queen of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sunday and Munday his Lordſhip went abroad to viſit diuers Nobles that had formerly been with him, as alſo ſpending ſome part of the ſame time in
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19287:24"/> concluding with the Councell of <hi>Spaine</hi> of matters concerning his Ambaſſage: and of all things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the effecting and performing the ſame.</p>
            <p>Tueſday the eight and twentieth day of <hi>May,</hi> his Lordſhip and all the reſt of the company were inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to dinner to the Duke of <hi>Lerma;</hi> where they were moſt honourably intertained, receauing there all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment that might be, for beſides the plenty of his cheare the manner of the entertainment could not be bettered. At the Table his Lordſhip was accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with the Duke of <hi>Lerma,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Infantaſgo,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Alberquerque.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They were attended vpon at this feaſt by diuers Nobles, Marqueſſes and Earles, with many Knights and Gentlemen of the Kings priuy chamber and few others.</p>
            <p>And beſides the ſeuerall ſorts of muſicke, during the time of dinner, his Lordſhip and the reſt hauing receiued what could be poſſibly giuen at the Table, they were caried downe into a faire court, paued with ſquare ſtone, in the middeſt whereof was a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of cleare water. The whole Court couered with canuas to defend and keepe off the heat of the ſunne, which at that time ſhone extreamly. In this Court was of purpoſe a ſtage erected, with all things fitting for a play, which his Lordſhip and the reſt were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uited to behold. The King and Queen being in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate likewiſe Spectators of that Interlude. To write of euery particular of the Dukes entertainment, were too much: for he tooke exceeding care to performe al things with the greateſt ſtate, as well appeared in this:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19287:25"/> that for that the kitchin was croſſe a ſquare Court, there were ſet vp high poſts of timber with canuas ſtrained, to couer and defend the ſame in the paſſage of the meat from the dreſſer. The ground being like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe couered with hangings of leather that no duſt ſhould ariſe whileſt the ſeruice paſſed by. At this feaſt ſeuerall Healths were druncke to the Kings of Great <hi>Brittaine</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> and to the happy continuance of the peace: begun by the Duke of <hi>Lerma,</hi> ſeconded by his Lordſhip, and performed by all the company at the table. Many Ladies of great account came pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uately to ſee and obſerue his Lordſhip and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany as they ſate at meat, well allowing and applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the plenty and bounty vſed at this feaſt, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſuch a one as the like was not ſeene in <hi>Spaine</hi> many yeares before.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday his Lordſhip concluded with the Conſtable and <hi>Alexander Rouida,</hi> Senatour of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine,</hi> as concerning all matters touching the taking of the Kings oath.</p>
            <p>Thurſday the thirtieth day of <hi>May,</hi> being <hi>Corpus Christi</hi> day, the King went in Proceſſion, and for that he would be ſeene by the Engliſh, the courſe was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the gate where his Lordſhip lodged. The manner was, as followeth:</p>
            <p>Firſt, came eight great Giants, three Men, three Women, &amp; two Mores with a Taber and Pipe play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and they dauncing. Then followed certaine Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimes clad in blew. After who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came many Croſſes, being in number, 25. or 26. borne &amp; attended by the officers of the ſeuerall Churches to which they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19287:25"/> Amongſt whom were alſo mingled diuers pictures of Saints: as Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> S. <hi>George</hi> killing the Dragon, Saint <hi>Michaell,</hi> Saint <hi>Francis,</hi> Saint <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew,</hi> Saint <hi>Dominicke,</hi> Saint <hi>Martin,</hi> the picture of Chriſt in ſeuerall formes, <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> our Lady in diuers faſhions alſo. Many holy and pretious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, Friers Mories dancers, in maner of Gypſies, beaſts with fire-works, Wild-men and ſuch like toies, as it ſhould ſeeme to draw the people more readily with admiration. After theſe followed diuers other Church reliques, Friers Auguſtines. Other Friers of the order of Saint <hi>Francis</hi> with their reliques. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Churchmen with lighted tapers in their hands; the Kings Pages bearing torches: Then the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments borne by foure Churchmen in rich Copes: Then the Lords and Grandes of <hi>Spaine;</hi> Then fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the King bearing a lighted taper of Virgin wax; after whom followed the Cardinall, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Ambaſſadour, the French Ambaſſadour, and the Venetian Ambaſſadour; the Prince of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Moroco</hi> and others, all bearing their tapers lighted in their hands.</p>
            <p>The ſame day his Lordſhip ſtaied till foure of the clocke after noone, vntill his Highneſſe pleaſure were knowen, that he was pleaſed as that day to take the oath formerly agreed on between them. About which time there came to his Lordſhip <hi>Don Blaſco de Aragon,</hi> who brought word that the King expected his Lordſhips comming to the Court as that day, and therefore for the more conuenient paſſage of the Nobles and Gentlemen that were to attend him thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19287:26"/> order was taken, that all ſhould be ſupplied with Gennets that wanted and would ſend to the Kings ſtable for the ſame. Euery man being furniſhed, his Lordſhip ſet forward to the Court, the Conſtable &amp; <hi>Don Pedro de Suniga</hi> being ſent to accompany his Lordſhip thither, as alſo diuers other Knights and Lords, whoſe names, for the ſodainneſſe of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming and the number of them being ſo many, could not be had. His Lordſhips owne Gentlemen were in ſeuerall coches afore and ſtaied at the Court gate expecting his Lordſhips comming thither, where likewiſe great preparation was made: diuers Noble men and others ſtaying there to receaue his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and his company. Amongſt whom were the Duke of <hi>Lerma</hi> and ſome other Grandes and thoſe of the greateſt Lords in <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Lordſhip being thus receaued, was conueied vp through a long Gallery into a Preſence, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another inner roome: the Gentlemen, Knights and Lords euer going before in very good order. In which roome his Maieſty ſtaied for the comming of his Lordſhip, receauing him with affable and kind congratulation, and tooke him along with him by his ſide. The Kings Sergeaunts at Mace going firſt, after following all the Graundes and Lords of <hi>Spaine</hi> one among another: then the foure Kings of Armes in their coats of Armes: then the Duke of <hi>Lerma</hi> bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Sword naked, wherein one thing is eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to be noted, that the Duke bare not the Sword vpright, as is the cuſtome of <hi>England,</hi> but bare it lying vpon his right ſhoulder: ſo the King and his Lords
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19287:26"/> went together into a very faire banquetting houſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry lately built, the Ambaſſadour Leadger, the Lords and diuers others following.</p>
            <p>The King ſitting in his Eſtate, his Lordſhip and the Ambaſſadour Leadger were placed vpon his left hand: the Grandes and other the Noblemen of <hi>Spaine</hi> being ſeated on the other hand, two degrees lower. Before the King was brought a little Table, whereon lay the Bible and a Crucifix vpon it. The Archbiſhop of <hi>Toledo</hi> read the oath with a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable loud voice: at one part of the oath his Lordſhip held the Kings hands between his: to which oath the King ſware kneeling and laying his hand vpon the Booke, and afterwards ſubſcribed to the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles and Agreements drawen and concluded by both Kings.</p>
            <p>Friday, the one &amp; thirtieth day of <hi>May,</hi> his Lordſhip dined early, for that there was that day appointed a ſport, which they call <hi>Inego de Toro,</hi> and alſo <hi>Inego de Canas:</hi> and for that his Lordſhip and all his company from the meaneſt to the higheſt, ſhould haue the pleaſure of the ſights, there were ſome appointed to ſee euery Engliſhman furniſhed of conuenient roome: which they did; <hi>Don Blaſco</hi> himſelfe taking an eſpeciall care and reſpect thereof. About the middeſt of the day came the King and Queen riding on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backe with many Lords and Ladies all on horſebacke likewiſe, after the Spaniſh faſhion, euery Lady ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with one or other man of worth: his Lordſhip was placed in the ſtanding with the King
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19287:27"/> and Queene; and the other Lords were placed not farre off. There were that day killed foureteene Buls; the maner whereof was in this ſort: Firſt, the market place, being very ſquare and of a great largeneſſe, was round built with Scaffolds very ſtrong; the ground couered very thicke with ſand, ſo that they were faine diuers times to bring in many carts of water, both to allay the duſt as alſo to coole the reflection of the ſunne vpon the place. In which, none were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be but ſuch as were deſigned to play the ſports. The Bull being turned out, they ſhotte ſticks with ſharpe pins and pricks which might ſticke faſt in his skinne, thereby the more madding him, he ſeemed to be moſt valiant that durſt afray the Bull in the face and eſcape vntouched: but ſome eſcaped not well, for it coſt them their liues. There was another maner of ſtriking the Bull in the face with ſhort ſpeares, to the which diuers Lords and Gentlemen very well mounted, their pages following them with diuers hand-ſpeares for that purpoſe; wherein many ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good valour, and ſtrake the Bull very cunningly and manly: but yet ſome of their Gennets payed deare for it, being both hurt and killed. To this ſport came two Gentlemen one after another, and as it was reported, ſupplying the places of Champions to the King, riding on horſes blinded, and ſo taking their ſtand, waiting for the comming of the Bull againſt them, very manly with a ſpeare of good length and ſtrength, ſtrake him in the head, and eſcaped with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hurt, though not being without danger.</p>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:19287:27"/>
            <p>After this, beganne their ſports of <hi>Inego de Canas,</hi> wherein the King himſelfe was an Actor. Firſt came riding twelue Drummers with Kettle-drummes play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; then followed thirtie Trumpetters, all clad in red and white ſilke coats; then followed twelue Açe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulaes or great Mules with couerings of red veluet, bearing bundles of Canes, tied and chained with great hooks of ſiluer: then followed the Kings Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and Pages richly ſuited, being to the number of two and thirtie or thereabout. After them were led by ſeuerall Groomes ſix and twentie riding horſes richly couered.</p>
            <p>For the two Princes of <hi>Sauoy</hi> were ſhewed: Firſt two Pages riding, bearing on their armes Targets all white: after whom were ledde three horſes couered with capariſons of blacke veluet imbrodered richly with pearle: then followed twelue other horſes, clad likewiſe in blacke veluet, but imbrodered with ſiluer.</p>
            <p>For the Duke of <hi>Lerma</hi> were led ſix horſes with capariſons of white and red: the Groomes and Pages attending, and all alike ſuited.</p>
            <p>For the Conſtable were led foure and twenty hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſeruice couered with white and greene: his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Groomes alſo alike ſuited.</p>
            <p>The number of horſemen that ſhewed themſelues in theſe ſports were foureſcore, whoſe names hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter follow, according to a note thereof deliuered by one of good woorth and of eſpeciall reſpect with the King.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:19287:28"/>
               <head>1. Quadrill.</head>
               <label>The King.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Duke of Lerma.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Duke of Cea.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conde de Gelues.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Marq. of S. German.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Don Hen. de Goſeman.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Conde de Mayalde.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Don Petro de Caſtro.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Marq. de la Veneſſa.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Don Garçia de Figuroea.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>2. Quadrill.</head>
               <label>Don Diego de Sandouall.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Antonio de S. Fago.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Alonſo Lopes de Mella.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Diego de Sebro.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Lewys de Alcarath.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Galuan.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Diego Nino.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Don Pedro de Aryetta.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Diego de Lieua.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Hieronomo de Sandouall</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>3. Quadrill.</head>
               <label>Duke of Infantaſgo.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Diego Sarmiento.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Conde de Baraſa.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conde de Paredes.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Conde de Coruna.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conde de Lodoſa.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Conde de Nieua.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Don Iuan de Taſsis.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>The Admyrall of Aragon.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Lewys Enriques.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>4. Quadrill.</head>
               <label>The Constable of Castilla.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marq. de Cuelar.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Conde de Aguillar.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marq. del Carpio.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Bernardino de Velaſco.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Fran. de Velaſco.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Antonio de Velaſco.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Alonſo de Velaſco.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Manuell de çuniga.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Andreas Velaſques.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19287:28"/>
               <head>5. Quadrill.</head>
               <label>The Duke of Alua</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conde de Salinas.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Marq. de Villanueua.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Martyn Valerio.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Pedro de çuniga S. de Flores.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Manuell de Alencaſtro.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Marq. de Tarara.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Diego Piementel.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Conde de Ayala.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marq. de çerralua.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>6. Quadrill.</head>
               <label>The Duke of Paſtrana.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Conde de Coſentagua.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Comendador Mayor de Monteſa.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Carlos de Borſa.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Marq. de Fuentes.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Lewys Nino.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Pedro de Fonſeca.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Ferdinand: de la Cerda.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Bernard de Rozas.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Iuan Vicentela.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>7. Quadrill.</head>
               <label>Conde de Alualiſta.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Bernard: de Toledo.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Fernando de Toledo.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Anto: de Toledo.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Philippo de Valencia.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Fran. Conguſta.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Lewys de Gozman.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Iuan de Gozman.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Marq. de Alcanes.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marq. de Fales.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>8. Quadrill.</head>
               <label>The Prince of Sauoy.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Prior of Ivan.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Mar. Doſte.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Diego de las marinas.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Fran. de Cordoua.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Iuan de Heredia.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Aluard de Mendoza.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Pero Mune.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>D. Franciſco Finea.</label>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Pedro de Licamo.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:19287:29"/>
            <p>At their firſt appearance they came riding in by couples two after two, very ſwiftly, richly attired with their Targets on their ſhoulders, holding and ſhaking long ſtaues ſuch as the Moores or Arabians are deſcribed to vſe. When they were all come, they diuided the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to ſides, euery ſide into foure ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons, euery ſquadron being tenne in number; when they were ready holding their ſtaues in their hands, the Kings ſide gaue the firſt charge; the other ſide vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking the ſame and charging on them likewiſe; thus they continued ſtill chaſing one another, ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron vpon ſquadron throwing their Canes one after other, by the ſpace of a long houre or better: and ſo their ſports ended.</p>
            <p>Saturday the firſt of <hi>Iune</hi> his Lordſhip was inuited by the King to ſee a muſter of armed men, in a place called <hi>El campo,</hi> being launces, light horſemen and Carbynes, to the number of two thouſand, whereof the Duke of <hi>Lerma</hi> was the Generall. His Lordſhip ſtood with the King and Queene, the reſt of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh were placed in a Scaffold, built for them of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: which ſaid ſouldiers being diuided made ſome ſhew of ſalies each vpon other, very pleaſingly and warlike: and after a few skirmiſhes, drew themſelues into a ring, and marching along vnder the window where his Maieſty ſtood, departed.</p>
            <p>Sunday, Munday and Tueſday were vſed as daies of reſt after their great feaſts: and ſpent onely in viſitation and matters of complement with one or other.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday his Lordſhip diſpatched Sir <hi>Iohn Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:19287:29"/> for <hi>England</hi> with letters of intelligence to his Highneſſe: who tooke with them the <hi>Aduantage,</hi> which lay at Saint <hi>Andreas</hi> with the reſt of the Shippes.</p>
            <p>Thurſday, the ſixth day of <hi>Iune,</hi> his Lordſhip was appointed both to dine and ſuppe early, which he did, becauſe both his Lordſhip, as alſo all other the Engliſh Lords and Gentlemen, were inuited to ſee a maske, about ſix of the clocke therefore came <hi>Don Blaſco</hi> to conduct his Lordſhip and the reſt through a priuate Gallerie of the Kings which ioined to his Lordſhips lodging, to the appointed place, which was the new built banquetting houſe formerly ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, by them termed the <hi>Grandſala:</hi> where was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed very conuenient roome for his Lordſhip and the reſt of his Followers. The roome was garniſhed with three hundred and twenty lights of wax, al ſet in ſtanderds of ſiluer, of diuers faſhions, ſome great and ſome ſmall. After two or three ſeuerall ſongs ſong by diuers voices in parts, placed ſeuerally in the ſame hall for that purpoſe; the maske appeared, and began as followeth:</p>
            <p>Firſt came thirty Muſitions clad in long garments of red Taffaty garniſhed well to the ſhew, playing on ſeuerall inſtruments. After whom followed ſix Virgins dauncing: one bearing in her hand a Sunne, another a braunch of Oliue-tree: another an Ancor: another a Sword with two points: on either point a bunch of flowers.</p>
            <p>Then followed a Charriot, made of an Antike faſhion, being drawen by two liue horſes, but excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19287:30"/> little. In the vpper part whereof ſate the <hi>Infanta,</hi> with a ſcepter of gold in her hand: with the picture of a doue on the vpper end thereof; at her feet ſate two other Virgins, who attended her. On either ſide went diuers Pages, bearing Torches of white wax.</p>
            <p>At the vpper end of the Hall was appointed a very rich State all of Maſons worke, aſcending vp by degrees richly gilded, and garniſhed with diuers ſtatues all gilt ouer; in which were planted three chaires: two great, and one leſſer, and that between the other two. In which middle chaire the Infanta being taken out from her Charriot was placed. The two Virgins neere her, and the other ſix vpon the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees at the foot of the Eſtate. At the neather end of the ſaid hall ſtood the Maskers in a Gallery contriued for the purpoſe, who vpon the drawing of a Curtyn, appeared as it were in clowds. The number of them were eight and twenty Knights and Ladies, beſide torch bearers, wherof the King and Queen were two: the reſt all Grandes and men of great Honour. The Ladies were all the Queens Maides. The ſaid Galle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being built in manner of an arch, and fully ſet with looking glaſſes, with the light of the torches ſhone as if it had been garniſhed with infinite number of ſtarres. The muſicke playing, the Maskers deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by foure and foure at a time in a ſtage made in faſhion of a clowde, and ſo dauncing to the vpper end of the Hall, before they could returne backe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther foure appeared, and ſo ioined altogether, vntill the number were come forth and then daunced al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19287:30"/> in good forme and meaſure.</p>
            <p>After diuers daunces and meaſures appointed of purpoſe for this ſhew; the King and Queen, and ſo likewiſe all the company, vnmasked themſelues; the King and Queen taking their ſeats in the places and chaires before mentioned: before whom were diuers Galiards daunced by the ſeuerall Lords and Ladies vnmasked. The Earle of <hi>Perth</hi> and the Lord <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oughby</hi> were inuited and daunced likewiſe. The King and Queen diuers times ſalied out from their chaires of Eſtate and daunced openly. At laſt they began a Calling daunce, which was begun by the Duke of <hi>Lerma</hi> holding a torch lighted in his left hand. The maner was; euery man called forth 2 women, chuſing one eſpeciall, conducted the other to her place, and left the choſen to call out 2. men, who likewiſe deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering the torch to one eſpeciall, conducted the other to his ſeat. Thus it paſſed to and fro amongſt many of the great Lords and Ladies; at laſt the King was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and his L. likewiſe; but the torch being deliuered to the King, his L. was againe brought to his ſeat. The King called forth the Queen and another, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a few trauerſes, when the time came he ſhould haue choſen and deliuered vp his torch, he deliuered it to a Page ſtanding by, and ſo the ſports ended.</p>
            <p>Friday, the ſeuenth of <hi>Iune,</hi> his L. was appointed to take leaue of the King, and ſo to ſet forward on his iourney for <hi>England;</hi> therefore taking notice of his L. deſire of returne, ordered he ſhould haue audience in the after noone. In the meane time his Highneſſe ſent by <hi>Don Pedro çuniga</hi> and ſome other, diuers
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19287:31"/> chaines of gold to the number of 14. or thereabouts, to ſome of the Kings ſeruants &amp; his L. chiefe officers: hauing likewiſe before ſent by <hi>Don Pedro çuniga</hi> vnto the Lords and many other Knights and eſpecial men of his L. company and traine ſeuerall Iewels and chaines, very rich. About foure of the clocke in the after noone, his Highneſſe ſent to his L. a very rich preſent of Iewels, both for himſelfe and his Lady, which were preſented to him by <hi>Don Blaſco</hi> and brought by the maſters &amp; officers of the Iewel houſe, who were by him well gratified and rewarded.</p>
            <p>Not long after, the Conſtable and others came to giue his L. knowledge of the conueniency of the time for our comming to the Court: whereupon his L. ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with the Lords, Knights, &amp; Gentlemen of his traine in ſeueral coches, went to the Court, where they were receaued by diuers Lords and Officers of the Court, at the Pallace gate, from whence the Kings guard made a paſſage euen to the kings Chamber. The King ſtaied to receiue his L. in a gallery, which was long but narrow, with whom his L. had confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in priuate by the ſpace of three quarters of an houre: and fearing to giue offence by tediouſneſſe, made motion to his Highneſſe, that the lords<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and others of his company might likewiſe take their leaues. The king very well pleaſed therewith; the Lords, Knights &amp; Gentlemen took their leaues, being generally well reſpected of his Maieſty. To conclude all, his L. tooke his leaue alſo, receauing many grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and kind words from his Maieſty, as alſo a ring with a Diamond, ſaid to be of the valew of 3000.
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19287:31"/> pounds, which he put vpon his L. finger, and as he ſaid in toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wedding him in true loue perpetually, commanding the Duke of <hi>Infantadgo,</hi> to conduct his L. and the reſt to the Queen in like manner to take their leaue of her Maieſty.</p>
            <p>Being brought to the Queen where ſhe ſate vnder a cloth of Eſtates with the Ladies &amp; Maids of honor, about her: for that it was late his L. made no long ſtay, after a ſhort time ſpent in complement tooke his leaue of her Highneſſe: as alſo, ſo did all other the Lords and Knights of his traine: to whom the Queen moſt reſpectiuely bowing her ſelfe, with much fauor and grace, gaue them a kind Farewell.</p>
            <p>His L. being now throughly furniſhed of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient meanes for his iourney, about 5. of the clocke the ſame day, being Saturday and the 8. day of <hi>Iune,</hi> ſet forward, being accompanied in his coch with the Conſtable &amp; diuers other noblemen in other coches, accompanying his L. a mile or more out of the town, where they taking their leaues departed. That night we rode 6. leagues to a towne called <hi>Duenas.</hi> The next day being Sunday we rode 9. leagues to a town called <hi>Fromiſta,</hi> where for that <hi>Don Blaſco</hi> and others were behind, his L. thought good to ſtay all Munday, leaſt the weather being very hot, might too much trouble them in riding poſt, and that were to come after. That night <hi>Don Blaſco,</hi> ouertooke his Lordſhip at <hi>Fromiſta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tueſday, the 11. of <hi>Iune,</hi> his L. dined at <hi>Oſorno,</hi> and ſomwhat late after dinner rode to <hi>Herrera</hi> to bed, where he was lodged in a faire houſe of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19287:32"/> of <hi>Caſtilla.</hi> Within this houſe are placed diuers pillars with letters engrauen after the maner of the Romane inſcription, &amp; ſo they plainly appeare to be monuments of the Romanes, and left as reliques of their being in that country.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday, the 12. of <hi>Iune,</hi> his Lordſhip rode from thence 8. leagues and lodged at a towne called <hi>Aguilar de Campo:</hi> the Marqueſſe of <hi>Aguilar</hi> being Lord thereof.</p>
            <p>Thurſday, we rode forward 7. leagues to a towne called <hi>Rynoſo:</hi> a towne ſeated in the middeſt of the mountaines.</p>
            <p>On Friday, his L. rode to <hi>Villa Concha</hi> to dinner, being 3. leagues and very ill way; after dinner we rode 4. leagues further to a towne called <hi>Villa Ciuil,</hi> to bed; being the worſt way and the worſt place of intertainment we had in the whole country of <hi>Spaine,</hi> being indeed ſeated amongſt mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains which harbor many beares, wolues &amp; other wild beaſts, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the country round about is much troubled.</p>
            <p>Saturday, the 15. day of <hi>Iune,</hi> we came to S. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreas</hi> being diſtant from <hi>Villa Ciuil</hi> 7. leagues, where his L. was receaued by the Magiſtrates and officers a mile out of the towne. All the ſtreets were ſtrawed with ruſhes and hearbs, and decked with bowes, and at his entrance into the towne, they gaue him many great ordinance, with volly of ſmall ſhot.</p>
            <p>That night the Ambaſſador Leadger, <hi>Don Pedro de çuniga,</hi> who accompanied the King to <hi>Burgos,</hi> came alſo to <hi>S. Andreas,</hi> where during the time of his ſtay, his L. expreſſed his bounty by rewarding <hi>Don Blaſco</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:19287:32"/> the <hi>Apoſentador</hi> and all the Kings other Officers and ſeruants with great chaines of golde, faire iewels of good value, and large ſummes of money, to their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall contentment.</p>
            <p>Sunday, Munday and Tueſday his Lo. reſted at <hi>S. Anderas,</hi> aſwell for that the horſes ſent by the King, his L. owne horſes, &amp; the Ambaſſador Leadgers hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes came not till Tueſday, as alſo for furniſhing the ſhips with freſh water and victuals for his returne for <hi>England.</hi> And on Sunday in the afternoone his Lo. inuited the <hi>Apoſentador Mayor, Don Blaſco de Aragon,</hi> and others, aboord the ſhips, where he made them a very great banquet; and at their going off ſaluted them with many pieces of ordinance.</p>
            <p>His L. hauing on Wedneſday the 19 of Iune, with all expedition that conueniently might be, ſhipped the horſes, and ſupplied the ſhips with all needfull prouiſions, about three of the clocke in the afternoon came aboord his ſhip called The Beare, lying at road a long Engliſh mile from the Towne, bringing alſo with him <hi>Don Pedro de çuniga,</hi> who taried and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with his Lordſhip that night. After ſupper his Lordſhip commanded his Barge to conuey him to his appointed lodging, which was in the Repulſe, where he entred, the Trumpets ſounding, and being ſaluted with many ſhot of great Ordinance.</p>
            <p>In the ſame road his L. ancored till Thurſday; and vpon Thurſday we put to ſea: but for that the tide was ſpent, and the winde falling out contrary, after an houre or two ſailing, we were driuen to caſt ancor; reſting that night till the next tide: at which time his
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19287:33"/> Lo: hoiſted ſaile and put to ſea, and with ſcant winde ſailed Friday and Saturday. On Sunday the weather fel out very foule and ſtormy, inſomuch as the Waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight ſpent in that ſtorme her maine maſt, but eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped further danger. Munday, Tueſday and Wedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day we ſailed but with very vnconſtant windes, being many times becalmed. On Thurſday afternoone the land was deſcried, but very farre off. That day and night we ſailed within ſight of land: and vpon Friday about foure of the clocke in the afternoone we came to an ancor before <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> but ſomewhat farre into the ſea. That night alſo came the Waſte-ſpight, who made great meanes to come ſo ſoone, hauing ſpent her maine-maſt, as is aforeſayd. Some of our company made hard ſhift that night to go on ſhore, enduring the hardneſſe of the weather, which fell out ill all that euening.</p>
            <p>On Saturday morning early his Lordſhip went in his Barge to the Repulſe, wherein <hi>Don Pedro</hi> was, and knowing that the ſayd <hi>Don Pedro</hi> much deſired to be on land, hauing indeed endured much ſickneſſe at ſea; tooke him into his Barge, and ſo with the company of ſome other Boats and Pynneſſes, came on ſhore at <hi>Portſmouth</hi> before eight of the clock in the morning, where they were receiued with many ſhot of great Ordinance from the Caſtles, Forts, and Walles of the Town. On the ſhore ſtood Sir <hi>Lewis Lewkus</hi> knight, accompanied with the Mayor and Officers of the Towne, ready to receiue the ſayd Ambaſſadours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as it ſhould ſeeme) appointed ſo to doe by the King and Lords of the Counſell. That day euery one
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19287:33"/> haſtened to get off their luggage from the ſhips, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring to goe forward likewiſe on their way toward <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day, being Sunday, his Lordſhip reſted there, went to the Church, and heard a ſermon pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly.</p>
            <p>Munday his Lordſhip hauing aſwell by meanes of the Kings officers and ſeruants, who were ſent for the purpoſe thither, as by his owne care, prouided for all neceſſaries to ſupply him in his iourney towards <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> about eleuen of the clocke ſet forward, riding in his Caroch, and taking the ſayd <hi>Don Pedro</hi> along with him: and ſo came that night to <hi>Alton,</hi> where they lodged that night.</p>
            <p>Tueſday the ſecond of Iuly, his L. rode from <hi>Alton,</hi> and lodged that night at <hi>Guilford,</hi> hauing taken eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care, both that <hi>Don Pedro</hi> the Ambaſſador Leid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, whom his Lo. had brought along in company, ſhould be reſpectiuely prouided for himſelfe as was fitting, as alſo all other his followers moſt plentifully ſupplied for all neceſſaries in their trauell, and that freely without charge or expence to any of them.</p>
            <p>Wedneſday they rode forward towards <hi>Kingston,</hi> where the <hi>Conde de Villamediana</hi> and others ſtayd ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the comming of the ſayd Ambaſſadour: and where alſo his Lordſhip had bountifully prouided for their entertainment in generall.</p>
            <p>Thurſday his L. hauing appointed the L. <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Effingham</hi> and ſome others of the better ſort to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the ſaid Ambaſſadour and the Conde <hi>de Villa mediana</hi> to <hi>London:</hi> he himſelfe with the reſt of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19287:34"/> his company rod for <hi>Windſor</hi> caſtle, where as then the King lay for his pleaſure of hunting, who there preſenting themſelues to his Maieſty, were of him moſt gratiouſly intertained and welcomed. At what time alſo his Lo. receaued further order from his Highneſſe when he would be pleaſed to giue audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the ſaid Ambaſſadour, and to admit him to his royal Preſence, according to appointment, which was accordingly performed, at the Court at White hall, on Sunday the 14. day of the ſaid moneth of <hi>Iuly</hi> following.</p>
            <p>Now for that it doth not fully appeare by this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer relation of his Lo. trauell &amp; iourney, how hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably and with what reſpect, he and his whole co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were receaued &amp; intertained: Ye ſhall vnderſtand, that firſt, vpon our landing at the <hi>Groyne,</hi> the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the country of <hi>Galicia,</hi> as is afore rehearſed; and as it ſhould ſeeme, by direct order from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; vpon the former arriuall of certaine ſhippes, wherein were the horſes and other preſents ſent from his Maieſty to the King of <hi>Spaine;</hi> had drawen toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther much people, and that of the better ſort of the whole country, of purpoſe to make ſhew both of the ſtrength of the country, as alſo to be the more ready to do ſeruice in ſupplying the Engliſh with all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries; and for this purpoſe alſo, their greateſt care was, that during our abode there, there might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare no want of any thing. His Lo. as is aforeſaid, was lodged in the Gouernors houſe, which of it ſelfe was very little, and not able to giue intertainment to ſo great a company. Therefore eſpeciall care was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19287:34"/> that euery man might according to his eſtate, be lodged as conueniently and as ſufficiently as the place would giue leaue. The towne being much decaied by reaſon of the late warres; nor as yet reedified ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thence the ſaccage thereof, by Sir <hi>Iohn Norrys</hi> and Sir <hi>Francis Drake.</hi> But we muſt acknowledge that for the greateſt part euery man was lodged there without exception. The care for lodging was not ſo much as was their exceeding care they had for prouiſion of victualls and viands to ſerue the companie: that countrie of <hi>Galicia</hi> being indeed verie mountainous and vnfruitfull. And therefore, although his Lo. was very ſufficiently prouided for at the Gouernours houſe, and that ſithence the roome there, being little, could not by any meanes ſupplie all: order was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that in euery houſe, wherein any Engliſhman lodged, prouiſion of diet was made for him and his ſeruants at the Kings proper coſt, wherein of neceſſity we muſt obſerue both the great charge, as alſo the great care, that was taken to ſupply all neceſſaries in the beſt faſhion: notwithſtanding which, there was daily prouided ſo large a table as conueniently could be, for all ſuch Knights and Gentlemen as would at their pleaſure come to attend and keep his Lo. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany at meat. This interteinment beginning the firſt day of our arriuall at the <hi>Groyne,</hi> which was the 16. day of <hi>April:</hi> and continuing all the time of our being in the <hi>Groyne,</hi> which was till the third of <hi>May</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what time we ſet forward on our land iourney, being then likewiſe furniſhed of Mules both for ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and cariage, all vpon the Kings charge.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:19287:35"/>
            <p>The number of Mules ſent to his Lo. for riding and cariage were 800. or there abouts, whereof 24. were great Aſſmuilas of the Kings prouiſion, and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for his Lo. owne cariages: beſide the mules for the Spaniards themſelues and their neceſſaries, which were eſteemed aboue 400. the Muletters to regard theſe Mules were numbred to be aboue 300.</p>
            <p>The company of Engliſh were accounted 650. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides theſe the king ſent many of euery office in court, ſome with the <hi>Apoſentador Mayor</hi> afore mentioned as diuers others <hi>Apoſentadors</hi> or harbengers; Stewards, Vſhers for the Chambers, Sewyers &amp; officers for the Table, officers of the Ewery, Pantry, Seller, Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry, 40. of the Spaniſh guard to ſerue the Table, cooke paſtelers, and ſuch like. Euery of theſe being particularly furniſhed with ſuch neceſſaries as belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to his office, as we might well perceaue, for that through the whole iourney, they were faine to carie by mules from place to place all the ſaid neceſſaries for their ſeruice, as plate, linnen, bedding, hangings, chaires, tables, formes, paſtry boards, kitchin furni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, racks, ſpits, pannes, and ſuch like: as alſo, moſt of their prouiſion of meale, wine, oile, vineger, herbs, fruit, ſweete-meates, and ſuch other. Wherein the ſaide officers, did ſo carefully and wiſely behaue themſelues, that it appeared there wanted no will in them either in care or paines, to giue content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the whole company of the Engliſh. This charge of the kings endured, vntill the returne of his Lordſhip to the ſhippes at S. <hi>Andreas:</hi> with very little difference either of meats or ſeruice at any time.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19287:35"/> Whither, for that the way from the <hi>Groyne</hi> was by experience found to be both long and ill, his Lo. had formerly directed the ſhippes to go, there to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide and ſtay his returne, being indeed not aboue halfe the way from <hi>Vallodelid,</hi> in compariſon of his iourney from the <hi>Groyne.</hi> Both in our going and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne we might well obſerue, how ioifull our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſeemed to the common people, both by their manner of behauiour, which was curteous, as alſo by their ſpeeches, which were moſt kind: who for that they found by experience the ill reports made hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of our nation altogether vntrue, admiring our ciuility and good behauiours; being cleane contrary to that which had been formerly preached vnto them by their Churchmen and Friers; we receaued that kind congratulation and vſage, that was poſſible for them to giue and vs as ſtrangers and trauailers to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue. Inſomuch, as well we obſerued as we paſſed, the countrey had taken exceeding care to make the waies both eaſie and pleaſing for vs to paſſe, digging downe hils in many places, and mending the waies with timber, ſtones and earth; no doubt to their great paines and charge.</p>
            <p>By which it moſt plainly appeared, with what ioy and comfort they receaued the peace generally, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſting the ſame aſwel by their deeds as words. And no doubt performed much more thankfulneſſe to their King for procuring it, than they would make ſhew of ioy to vs for obtaining it.</p>
            <p>And yet what words might expreſſe, that might we daily heare, for we might obſerue, how they prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19287:36"/> the ſame in pulpits and ſpake of the ſame euen in their open plaies and Interludes, making, as they ſaid, many feaſts and ioies for the bleſſed peace.</p>
            <p>The bounty of the King in gifts aſwell to his Lo. as to diuers other of his followers, together with the great charge his Highneſſe was at during our aboad there, gaue vs not ſo good contentment in generall, as did the good eſteeme and behauiour we found in all from the higheſt to the meaneſt, vpon euery oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion miniſtred to them to ſhew the ſame: either in particular or in generall. His Lo. receauing all very thankfully, and not without a reciprocall ſhew of his bounty and good will againe, being indeed of his purſe not ſparing, and (with pardon be it ſpoken) as liberall in his degree as was neceſſary: whoſe cariage and behauiour during the whole iourney being ſuch, and vpon good intelligence, ſufficiently knowen to his Maieſty, who imploied him, and by him is both gratiouſly allowed and accepted; he himſelfe hath cauſe ſufficient of gladneſſe, and no other cauſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception in any ſort. So concluding with the bleſſing of our Sauiour, <hi>Beati pacifici,</hi> let vs pray to Almighty God to make his Maieſty as careleſſe of warre, as hee from time to time in his great iudgement ſhall finde peace to be neceſſary; his people and ſubiects euer obedient to all his deſignes and appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments either in warre or peace, and his Maieſty himſelfe bleſt with long life, health and ability to vndergoe either, as it ſhall ſeeme beſt to the diuine Maieſty. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19287:36"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
